So, I realize that there's a lot of
people that believe that a ketogenic
diet will eradicate cancer. And in the
same vein, fasting will also eradicate
cancer. Well, as you'll see, that may
not always be the case. But, as I've
said many times before, we wouldn't want
nuance to get in the way of the blinding
light of simplicity. Still, I'll dare to
introduce this brand new detailed study
indicating the potential harm of a
ketogenic diet for cancer. But it isn't
all bad news, as I'll explain. You may
have heard of a famous researcher by the
name of Dr. Otto Warberg, who over 100
years ago discovered that cancer cells
preferentially use glucose, that's blood
sugar, for energy. Then many decades
later, other scientists have taken that
foundational idea and further
substantiated it. Even recently, there's
been quite a push to recognize cancer as
a metabolic disease. While that whole
arc is a little beside the point here,
it does tell us that there's plenty of
research and well-accepted research that
indicates that cancer cells feed on
glucose. On the other hand, there's been
a hard swing in the opposite direction.
Then if cancers prefer glucose, why not
just reduce the glucose that cancer has
access to? And why not use an
alternative fuel source that the rest of
our body can use? But presumably cancer
can't, and that is ketones. Ketones
metabolize molecules produced by our
liver when we fast for long periods of
time or stick to a very strict very low
carbohydrate, i.e. ketogenic diet are
produced from fat. And given what I
mentioned previously, it makes sense
that they'd be unusable or difficult to
use by cancer cells, giving us the
metabolic upper hand. However, something
that cancer biologists know that the
public doesn't generally consider is
that tumors, abnormal masses of cancer
cells, have different requirements
depending on which section of the tumor
that you're looking at. For example,
some areas of a tumor can be
vascularized quite well, meaning blood
flow containing glucose, oxygen, and
more flows to those cells quite easily,
offering a non-stop flow of nutrients.
However, in the very same tumor, another
section can be poorly vascularized. So,
less of everything arrives. In such a
case within the same tumor, the same
types of cancer cells can need different
things as well as react to different
stimuli. So what I'm trying to say in
now fewer words, cancer is way more
complex than is often explained. Taking
that background into account, when we
look at cancer cells, we can split them
into two categories. To be clear, we
could divide them into many more
categories, but we'll stick to these two
for now. One category is called adherent
cells. The second category is called a
tumor initiating cell. The adherent
cells tend to make up the bulk of the
tumor and the tumor initiation cells
make up the minority. Now, think of it
like a like a beehive. The majority of
the bees, the worker bees are the
adherent type of cancer and the queen
bee is the middle of the hive. The
worker bees, the adherent cancer cells,
divide very quickly and keep growing the
tumor. But if the entire tumor was
destroyed, it would be the queen bee,
the tumor initiation cancer cell, that
could recreate the entirety of a new
tumor. They're rare but powerful cancer
cells. Now, another one of their powers
is their metabolic flexibility, meaning
if the blood supply changes or the
nutrient delivery changes, they can
adapt extremely well. So when we look at
the tumor growth in human tumors, the
higher the lines go, the larger the
cancerous tumor. And we see that those
exposed to a ketogenic diet defined as
only 3% of the diet coming from
carbohydrates and almost 60% from
dietary fat, there is a rapid
acceleration of the tumor. You can see
the images of the excise tumor on the
left, non- ketogenic exposed up top and
ketogenic exposed on the bottom. There's
clearly a size difference. So the main
point up to now is that a ketogenic diet
applied to patient tumors leads to
faster tumor growth. Now the reason for
that accelerated growth is due to the
specific effects that ketones have on
these tumor initiation cancer cells.
They tend to speed up their growth. In
fact, these cancer cells become in a
manner of speaking addicted to ketones.
Not just because they use them for
energy generation, but also because they
can reroute these ketones to be used in
building blocks for the generation of
fat to create cell membranes for the
cells called lipogenesis.
But there's a critical defining feature
that makes this more or less of a
problem. That feature is the cell's
production of a transport protein and
its stabilizing protein that allow
ketones into the cell. for your cells to
even allow ketones into them to be used.
In this cancer case, we're talking about
energy generation as well as lipogenesis
to produce more cell membranes. They
must have a gateway to enter the cell
through the cell membrane. That protein
is called MCT1 and it's stabilized by a
protein called CD47.
And you don't need to know the names.
just know that there's a transporter
that allows ketones into the cell to be
used. So, it makes logical sense that
when we look at tumors, we can assess
their dependence or eagerness to rely on
ketones for energy. And when looking at
normal lung tissue versus cancerous lung
tissue from the tumor, there are
elevated levels of these proteins. Now,
beyond that and more suggestive of a
potential unique effect, when looking at
people with cancer, we see striking
findings. This is a survival curve. So,
all you need to know is that if the
lines are higher up and further to the
right, that's better survival from
cancer. The red line is the people with
lung cancer that has high expression or
levels of these ketone transport
proteins. And the black line is those
with similar cancer but lower expression
of these proteins. Clearly, the presence
of these proteins could mean something.
One, this tells us that there may be a
unique harm for those with cancers that
express high levels of these ketone
transport proteins. Two, it also tells
us that a ketogenic diet may not be
universally negative as it may depend on
the expression of these proteins. The
main point here is that ketones are used
by some cancer cells for energy
generation and for the generation fat
molecules to be used in the creation of
new cell membranes i.e new cancer cells.
Now beyond that some of this may depend
on if the cancer produces a lot of these
ketone gateways. Okay, let me pause here
and also mention that this association
is a simple one. There may be other
reasons that these people experience
faster cancer progression, but in the
totality of evidence, it fits with the
direct evidence presented throughout
this study. So, where does that leave
us? What do we make of all this? Well,
let me get into that next. But if you're
looking for a more detailed analysis
getting into the mitochondrial aspects
of these cancer cells and what happens
when we block these transport proteins
or even what researchers are starting to
hint toward in relation to how approach
these cancers, I cover all that in the
extended analysis that I offer in an
extended video format like what you're
watching right now, but also in an
article and even in a podcast format.
That's all included for the Physionic
Insider member, plus all these benefits
right here. If you're interested, check
out the Physionic Insiders membership in
the description. I hope to see you
there. This leaves us in a seemingly off
situation because on one hand, there are
also studies that show that ketogenic
diets and generally raising ketones like
fasting can diminish tumor growth. And
yet, we then see studies like this one,
and there are others that indicate worse
outcomes. So, how do we reconcile those
differences? Well, for one, these
studies tend to look at different forms
of cancer. The cancers where ketogenic
diets seem helpful in combating cancer
are certain pancreatic cancers and colon
cancers. Meanwhile, glyopblastoomas,
melanomas, and as we saw here, lung
cancers are better off without ketones
present. So, could the type of cancer be
the defining feature? It seems a strong
possibility at least. Second, a lot of
these studies, including this one, rely
on mouse data. So, we went over some
human data, but even then, it was simple
associations and mechanisms, so we need
more translational evidence. I'm not
sure how feasible that will be
considering the ethics, but maybe
there's a way around that. Here's what I
make of it. A ketogenic diet is still a
perfectly viable path to use in general
health and even against cancer. I don't
think that these data are enough to
dissuade against that. However, I would
be cautious believing that a ketogenic
diet is the solution to all cancers and
making sure if you have cancer that the
data tends in the direction that your
diet choice is beneficial in combating
that specific cancer. And here we saw
mechanistic and weak associative
evidence that a ketogenic diet
accelerates certain lung cancers.
Certainly more direct clinical data is
needed to confirm these findings. But
speaking of cancer, there's plenty of
other material on how to think and deal
with cancer that I go over right here.
Thanks for tuning in as always. I deeply
appreciate it. I hope to catch you in
the next one. Bye.